Guide to the Right Wing Pamphlet collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- PRINTED MATTER FROM THE JOHNSON COLLECTION, 1917-1966; Series I; 5' 10" (14 boxes)
  - Taxation, 1956-1961, undated (Box 14, Folder 228)
  - Unions, 1951-1963, undated (Box 14, Folder 229)
  - United Nations, 1953-1963, undated
  - Vietnam, 1953-1963, undated (Box 14, Folder 230)
  - Walker, Major General Edwin A., 1961-1963, undated (Box 14, Folder 231)
  - World War II and Postwar Problems, (1940)-1958, undated (Box 14, Folder 232)
- ACCESSIONS AFTER 1976-M-XXX, Series II
  Series II is arranged by accession: each new item is assigned a box and folder number upon its arrival. Where possible items will be grouped by subject or the name of the issuing organization.
  - [Economics]
    - A series of pamphlets issued by the Foundation for Economic Education, Irvington-on-Hudson:
      - Bastiat, Frederic: The Law, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Curtiss, W.M.: The tariff idea, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Fairchild, Fred Rogers: Profits and the ability to pay wages, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Hazlitt, Henry: Will dollars save the world?, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Poirot, Paul L.: The pension idea, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Rogers, Sherman: Why kill the goose, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Russell, Dean: The TVA idea, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 233)
      - Von Mises, Ludwig: Planned chaos, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 233)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets:
      - A primer of capitalism. Illustrated. New York, J.Walter Thompson Company, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - Scoville, John W.: Labor monopolies or freedom. New York, Committee for Constitutional Government, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - Spahr, Walter E.: Our irredeemable currency system. New York, Economists' National Committee on Monetary Policy, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - White, Andrew Dickson: "Fiat money inflation in France," The Freeman v.2, no.3, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - Borsodi, Ralph: Inflation is coming! and what to do about it. Suffern, N.Y. School of living, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - Spahr, Walter E.: The urgent need for monetary statesmanship. NewYork, Economists' National Committee on Monetary Policy, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 234)
      - Reformed Illuminati Group. Mrs. Esther Dunlap, President. Greenwich, Conn. Statements issued in the form of open letters to public figures on political and social issues. 43 items, 1968-1972 (Box 15, Folder 235)
- Additional material, 1937-2010; Accession 2016-M-017; 1.58; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The materials are arranged alphabetically.
  This accession consists of booklets, leaflets, brochures, comic books, and other ephemera created by a variety of right wing reactionary groups, including anti-communist, white supremacist, anti-semitic, fundamentalist Christian, and American nativist organizations, as well as the John Birch Society.
  - America First Committee, Northern California Headquarters, Handbill with statement of principles and application form, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Conservative Union, "The Nixon Welfare Plan. A Guaranteed Annual Income... What It Means to YOU as a Taxpayer.", Circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Four-panel brochure, with cover photo of welfare activists protesting in Washington, expressing rRight-wing criticism of Nixon's plan.
  - American Economic Foundation, "The Ten Pillars of Economic Wisdom", Circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Eight-panel brochure that lists the "ten pillars," which were put on display at the NY World's Fair in 1964, and introduces the Foundation.
  - American Education Lobby, "Have Our Schools Been Sold to the US Government?", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Six-panel brochure published by group formed in response to federal school integration mandates.
  - American National Party. KILL! Magazine: Dedicated to the Annihilation of the Enemies of the White People, Vol. 1, no. 1-2, 1962 July-September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This short-lived group led by John Patler, erstwhile comrade and later assassin of neo-Nazi leader George Lincoln Rockwell, published only four issues before Patler reunited with Rockwell's group. Illustrated with black and white photos, the inaugural issue includes a piece by Burros, "The importance of killing," while much of the second issue is devoted to Patler's arrest for his role is breaking up a "race-mixing rally" in Englewood, New Jersey. Other articles include "White woman stabbed, beaten, robbed while praying in church: How much more 'brotherhood' will the Whiteman take?" and "Black criminal slashes White mother's throat in rape attempt."
  - American National Party, New York Division, "Notice! Street Meeting! To Protest the Red 'Peace Meeting' at St. Nicholas Palace", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Handbill announcing one of the pieces of far-right street theater put on by the short-lived group led by John Patler, speaking on "We Want War with Communism ... Not Peace!" R. G. Grandinetti, New York State Chairman, American National Party also appeared.
  - American Taxpayers' Union, Oakland, California, The Taxpayer: Official Publication, 1967 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Five page document discusses tax issues at the local level. It includes a list of businesses that support the ATU.
  - Bader, Salem." Let's Go to War Again! A G.I. Indicts Mr. and Mrs. America", Circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    16 page anti-Semitic tract lamenting America's recently concluded role in World War II; argues that regardless of whether the enemy is called Fascism or Communism, it's all a charade to make Americans fight for the "sinister hand lurking in the shadows, pulling the strings to which our marionette politicians dance." Bader had worked with Lawrence of Arabia in the British Intelligence Service, settling in the US in 1925 and becoming a citizen in 1942. His anti-Zionist activism culminated in establishing the United States Arab-Asian Institute in 1953.
  - Britton, Frank L., "Emergency Message: "Civil Rights" Bill May Pass!", 1950s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Broadside containing plea for funds to defeat the pending Civil Rights bill, backed by the NAACP and the ""Jewish owned" New York Times, with the funds being sent to Britton.
  - Brownlee, George, ed., "The Sandtown Story, Bulletin 85", 1966 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Privately printed newsletter of sardonic anti-Semitic, anti-Black, anti-Catholic, anti-Communist political commentary and humor. This issue includes letters from subscribers who are cancelling because, on top of the aforementioned tendencies, the publisher ran an anti-Masonic piece.
  - Bubb, Frank, "What Causes War? Those Who Oppose War Must Discover Its Premises", 1970s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Brochure that argues that the only moral reason for opposing war it its violation of individual rights. It includes text of the Society for Individual Liberty Declaration of Principle adopted October 1969.
  - Bunch, Paul, "The Masterminds of Stonehenge", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Document argues that the builders of Stonehenge were members of a noble White Race rather than savages. It was published by a Christian Identity outfit.
  - Caughey, A.W., "The Pulse of Capitalism", 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Sixteen issues (1996: nos. 1, 2, 4; 1997: 1-4; 1998: 1-4; 1999: 1-4; 2000: no. 1) of a quarterly newsletter containing occasionally contrarian economic analysis.
  - Christian Crusade, "A Call to Action to Every Real American. HELP Stop Communism, Save America from Socialism, Preserve Freedom", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Brochure introduces the Crusade, founded by Billy James Hargis, and its anti-communist mission.
  - Christian Crusade, "...Don't Just Throw Up Your Hands... Do Something... Help Billy James Hargis Fight Communism", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    This is an eEight-panel brochure opening up to an illustrated pricelist of the Crusade's anti-communist publications.
  - Christian Crusade, "This is Christian Crusade: A Christian Anti-Communist Ministry", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This is an eight-panel brochure introducing the Crusade's anti-communist mission.
  - Christie, Roy S. and Hal Stearley, "This is a free ticket. It's not good for anything, it's just free. Compliments of The Great Society.", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Parody ticket with poem by Christie on verso that mocks the Great Society as a plan led by a Pied Piper that will lead sheeplike Americans to slavery.
  - Coffman, Michael S., "Property Rights the Foundation of Freedom: The Feudal Nature of Federal Regulations", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Six-panel brochure that argues that federal regulations have actually undercut environmental protection as well as personal liberties.
  - Committee for Defense of Property Rights and Students for Columbia University, Handbills and broadsides issued in the wake of the SDS seizure of buildings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    There are four mimeographed handbills and two larger broadsides reprinting full-page ads taken out in the Columbia student paper by the Committee. One handbill titled "S.D.S.: TODAY'S VERSION OF NAZI THUGS" states that "The announced long-range purpose of the rebels is a collectivist society indistinguishable in principle from the Fascist regimes of the 20th century... The members of the Committee for Defense of Property Rights therefore call for strict enforcement of the law at Columbia by prosecuting the rebel leaders for the crimes they have committed: vandalism, criminal trespass, corecion, extortion, and unlawful imprisonment."
  - "Communism Today: What Every American Should Know about It", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Concerned Citizens Against Sexual Orientation Ordinances, "Fact: Enough Is Enough. No on A and B. Keep It Private", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Campaign brochure that opposes two measures that would have banned anti-gay discrimination in San Jose, arguing that they are part of a concerted effort to bring San Francisco values to the south bay. It includes a facsimile reproduction of a flyer distributed at high schools allegedly recruiting boys into the gay lifestyle (actually a support group for gay teens), and lists of "facts" to prove there is no discrimination against gays in the law, thus no need for the two ballot measures.
  - Conservatives for Marchi, Cards for "charter members" of the "Retire John Lindsay Club", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This consists of six unused wallet-sized cards on blue stock still attached together with blank space for owner's name.
  - Dedham TACT Committee, "Peace Symbols: The Truth about Those Strange Designs", Circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Handbill that outlines the alleged Communist and Satanic origins of the peace symbol, depicting Bertrand Russell as the central figure in its sinister development. Adapted to a significant degree from David Emerson Gumaer's John Birch Society piece, "Peace Symbols"., but designed to fit on both sides of a single sheet.
  - "Eagle Forum, Leading the Pro-Family Movement to Victories since 1972", Circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Six-panel brochure introducing the group led by Phyllis Schlafly is from the ssecond Reagan administration.
  - Emry, Sheldon, "Jesus Christ the Galilean", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    ract by the Christian Identity preacher arguing that Jesus was not Jewish, based on a 1979 sermon (34 pages).
  - Emry, Sheldon, "Who Killed Christ?", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    This is an aAnti-Semitic tract by the Christian Identity preacher.
  - Everingham, Harry T., "The Fact Finder", 1962-1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Seventeen issues of the publication, all in the form of an eight panel brochure on a particular topic, including the Cuban threat, "Why the left wing wants to smear Goldwater," the Supreme Court's red agenda, the 1979 fuel crisis as a plot to make Americans easier to control, and the banning of prayer in schools as national suicide. One, on the assassination of the communist lackey Martin Luther King Jr., is paper clipped to a printed letter signed in pen by J. S. Selden emphasizing the importance of circulating this particular issue to alert Americans to King's enmity towards "our Christian Republic." Issues present are: Vol. 21 nos. 2, 4 and 14; vol. 22 nos. 9 and 15; vol. 23 no. 15; vol. 24 no. 4; vol. 26 nos. 9 and 11; vol. 27 no. 23; vol. 28 no. 22; vol. 29 no. 2, vol. 37 nos. 16 and 17; vol. 38 no. 7; vol. 52 no. 5, and an unnumbered issue.
  - Exclusive: the Fulton Lewis Jr. Newsletter, Wallet card outlining spending, 1935-1958, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Small stiff card designed to fit in a wallet or pocket, printed with text on both sides, provides statistics outlining the rise in spending under the New Deal and the subsequent fall in government spending under the Republicans, rising again under Eisenhower, intended to prove that Eisenhower betrayed conservative spending principles.
  - Foundation for Economic Education, "Notes from FEE", 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Thirteen issues of the newsletter, 4 pages each, include September 1974; January, March, May, June, September and November 1975; January, March, May, July, September, and November 1976, and March 1977. Also included is a pamphlet about 1977 Summer Seminars and a postcard depicting the building in which the Foundation was based.
  - Gayman, Dan, "The Two Seeds of Genesis 3:15", Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Christian Identity viewpoint asserts self-proclaimed Jews are actually "Synagogue of Satan." Includes two pages introducing Gayman's church, The Church of Our Christian Heritage, in Missouri and its day school for racially aware Christian children. Gayman published a full-length book on this topic.
  - George Romney Campaign Reporter, 1968 January 26 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Campaign brochure in tabloid newspaper format, with headline above the fold: "Romney's spirits rise after swing through NH," is from early in the race for the Republican nomination, which he eventually lost to Richard Nixon.
  - "Give to anti-communist candidates: they need our help" stamps, Undated; Perforated sheet of 15 stamps, called "cinderellas" in philatelic jargon is 3.75x5 inches, stamp size is roughly 1x1.25 inches. Back not gummed, never hinged. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gun Owners' Action League, "One Anti-Gun Legislator Can Ruin Your Whole Day...", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Six-panel brochure with caricature of Teddy Kennedy on cover, that provides history and goals of the organization, a pro-gun lobbying group. The funds for printing are stated to have come from Smith and Wesson.
  - Haviland, Dave; editor, "A is A. Writings on Freedom and Individualism", 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    The four issues of the digest-sized newsletter, 8 pages each, are vol. 3 nos. 2-5.
  - Hazlitt, Henry, "Instead of What? Government Can't Give Us Anything without Depriving Us of Something Else", Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Hear Kenneth Goff, former Communist leader, expose Communism in California Southland", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Handbill announcing a series of talks at the Embassy Auditorium at 9th and Grand. Topics are "Red treason in Californai Schools," "God's answer to the racial crisis," and "From Communism to Christ," heralded as the speaker's life story.
  - The Herald of the America First Committee of Northern California, 1941 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    This issue promotes an upcoming address by Burton K. Wheeler.
  - "International Press News Brief, June 5, 1985", Circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Parody of the liberal policies of the Kennedys projected into the future.
  - Jewish Society of Americanists, "Statement of Principles", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Statement begins with "We, Jewish members of the John Birch Society, have formed the Jewish Society of Americanists, in order to demonstrate to our fellow Americans and co-religionists, that the Americanist principles, beliefs and aims of the John Birch Society are based on the very precepts of Judaism which have become part of the foundation of our Western civilization..." Text originally appeared in two issues of the Bulletin of the John Birch Society. Provides contact address and names of leaders.
  - John Birch Society, Three color photographs from chapters, Circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Snapshots, one depicting an "Impeach Earl Warren" billboard, with a paper label pasted to the bottom of the photo noting that the sign was erected by chapter 729 on route 20, 20 miles west of Richmond; the other two photos show patriotic memorabilia and books on display in a shop, with pen notation on the back indicating that they show a California bookstore, possibly inside the home of a member named "Eliz...?"
  - John Birch Society, "The John Birch Society, Incorporated, presents its founder, Mr. Robert Welch, speaking on The Tragedy of Vietnam", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Leaflet with American flag motif announcing eventa is a on October 10, with text on verso about how Welch "Has stirred the slumbering spirit of patriotism in thousands of Americans..."
  - Johnston, "Parson Jack," Paul Lupo,and Gerald B Winrod, "Labor: Dangers of the C.I.O. Movement", 1937 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    General
    Johnston, president of the Fundamentalist Bible College, edited "The Trumpet".
  - Kamp, Joseph P., "Lawless Tyranny an American Conspiracy, Against We the People. Plus Behind-the-Scenes Facts about the Red-led Racist Revolution", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Kamp, opposed to the Civil Rights movement, composed this a 111 page polemic against Martin Luther King, Walter Reuther, Bayard Rustin, Jack O'Dell, etc.
  - Kibbe, Matt, "Rules for Patriots: A Pocket Primer for Patriotic Americans", 2010 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    This is a Tea Party organizing manual.
  - "Knockout the blackout over America," advertising copy for John Beaty's "Iron Curtain Over America", Circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    This single page of copy, possibly written by Beaty himself, warns that constitutional government is being crushed by "the snake of Zionistic Communism."
  - McManus, John F., "Dollars & Sense: Solutions to the Economic Meltdown", 2009 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - McManus, John F., "The John Birch Society: Reality vs. Myth", 2011 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Middleton, Richard H., Campaign leaflets, 1961, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    A 1961 flyer from Middleton's first campaign for the House of Delegates, accusing his opponent of insufficient support for states' rights, and a six-panel brochure from his 1963 re-election campaign, better printing quality with a photo on the front panel, listing his hard-right positions of various issues including opposition to "creeping socialism," civil rights marches, and local issues such as farm taxation.
  - The Mindszenty Report\, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Five issues (August 15, 1963; March 15, 1970; January 1971; December 1976; and May 1985) of the anticommunist Cardinal Mindszenty's newsletter, covering themes of the need for the US to keep the Panama Canal, the communist subversion in the musical "Hair," rock and revolution, and the abominable state of Africa due to communist influence.
  - National Association for the Advancement of White People, NAAWP News, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Issue no. 24 was a special "sampler issue" sent out to prospective subscribers. It includes a substantial interview with David Duke.
  - "National Republic Lettergram, No. 259", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    This issue, headlined "UNESCO prods educators to brainwash American youth," is devoted to UNESCO and the "internationalization" on the educational curriculum, arguing that under UN influence American children are having their patriotic inclinations squashed in favor of creeping one-worldism.
  - National Youth Alliance, "What is NYA?", Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Eight-panel brochure introducing the far-right student and youth group "inspired by the pro-Western philosophy of Francis Parker Yockey's masterpiece, Imperium" includes a collage of newspaper headlines on the group and its action units, formed to fight leftists.
  - New England Rally for God, Family and Country programs, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    "From '76 to 1966, the Spirit of Independence calls you back" program for the 1966 event, with a list of exhibitors (many John Birch Society projects but some further right) has right edge dyed red and left untrimmed to give an "antique" appearance. Brochure for the 1965 rally is less elaborate.
  - Nolan, William A., "Why People Go Communist", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Northern California Citizens Against 30-Thursday, "Hoaxing the Hungry!", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Front page continues with "The story of California betrayed for 30 pieces of paper. If you value your home, your business, your job and the security of your family, read this startling expose of the 30-Thursday pension scheme." This is a Pro-business attack on the "Ham and Eggs" proposition.
  - Oliver, Revilo P., "After Fifty Years", Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Four-panel brochure published by National Youth Alliance marking the time since the first anti-communist groups were formed.
  - Overstreet, Harry and Bonaro Overstreet, "What We Must Know About Communism", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This condensation of a larger work was printed for General Motors employees.
  - Patler, John, "Here Comes Whiteman", Circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Comic book format, printed on newsprint, has an issue title of "Whiteman fights an interplanetary duel with a diabolical fiend... The Jew from Outer Space. Whiteman also battles Supercoon!" The masthead states "Jew commies tremble. Nigger criminals quake in fear. Liberals head for the hills."
  - The Patriot, "The Joyride to Slavery", Circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Anti-Semitic and anti-communist leaflet referring to Jews as the Pharisaic Conspiracy. "By means of phony promises of a 'worldly Paradise" we working people of the world are being slyly lured into the most terrible, the most inescapable slavery ever devised by the mind of man... Maybe by now you know how these flabby, bald, hooked-nosed, evil-eyed, insulting, lecherous slobs bribe our most luscious daughters to serve them as their sexual maid-servants..."
  - Peters, Peter J., "Martin Luther King Jr.: His Dream, Our Nightmare!", 1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Peters, Peter J.. "Saving the Environment, New World Order Style", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This anti-Semitic and anti-environmentalist pamphlet contains significant Christian Identity material.
  - "The Plot to Impose "Black Supremacy" Upon the South", Circa 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    One page broadside, which includes black and white illustrations of Black representatives of southern states from the 19th century, argues that the NAACP, controlled by "aliens" (ie, Jews), is pushing for the forced governance of southern whites by Black leadership.
  - Power, Thomas S., "General Thomas S. Power's Design for Survival", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    This is a comic book adaptation of the anti-communist book.
  - Rand, Ayn, "The Cashing-In: The Student "Rebellion" New York", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    This is a mockery of the Free Speech Movement, originally published as a series in The Objectivist.
  - Rand, Ayn, "Conservatism: An Obituary", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    This is a reprint of a lecture delivered at Princeton, December 7, 1960.
  - Rand, Ayn, "Faith and Force: The Destroyers of the Modern World", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    A reprint of a lecture originally delivered at Yale University on February 17, 1960, as a guest speaker of the Yale Law School Forum and Challenge, the undergraduate lecture committee.
  - Rand, Ayn, "Textbook of Americanism", 1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Reprint of articles originally written for the Motion Picture Alliance for the Preservation of American Ideals in 1946.
  - Rand, Ayn, "What Is Capitalism?", Late 1960s (Box 2, Folder 12)